Guide to the Nathan Carter Newbold family papers, 1848-1952 and undated RL.11544
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nathan Carter Newbold family papers
1848-1952 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11544
3.5 Linear Feet
North Carolina family active in education, law enforcement, farming, and slavery. The bulk of the papers relate to Nathan Carter Newbold and his relatives, including his father William A. Newbold and grandfather William Newbold (Sheriff of Pasquotank County, North Carolina), his first wife Mabel Wooten, and his second wife Eugenia Bradsher. Nathan Carter Newbold was the Director of the Division of Negro Education for the North Carolina State Department of Public Instruction from 1913-1950. The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, photographs, financial and property records dating from the 1840s, and recorded speeches given at Nathan Carter Newbold's retirement dinner. Some photographs have been identified as being of South Carolina during the late 19th century-early 20th century, which include portraits, street scenes (in Charleston), sail boats, as well as a few photographs of people of color, including photographs of "Lascar Sailors."Some photographs are of the U.S. Military Academy at West Point during the 1890s. Many of the legal and financial papers were generated by Nathan Carter Newbold's father and grandfather. The bulk of the correspondence relates to Nathan Carter Newbold's role as an administrator for North Carolina public schools and to his tenure as the Director of the Division of Negro Education during segregation and Jim Crow.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Legal and Financial papers, Photographs, Printed Materials and Ephemera, and Writings and Speeches. Correspondence and Writings and Speeches are arranged alphabetically. Some of the photographs are arranged by geographic location.
Biographical / Historical
Nathan Carter Newbold was the Director of the Division of Negro Education for the North Carolina State Department of Public Instruction from 1913-1950. Born in 1871 in Pasquotank County, N.C., Newbold lived and worked in North Carolina most of his life. He attended Trinity College (now Duke University) in 1895 and went on to work in education at schools across North Carolina first as a teacher, principal, and superintendent, and then as the Director of the Division of Negro Education in Raleigh during segregation and Jim Crow. He was a founding member of the North Carolina Commission for Interracial Cooperation and served as director of the Division of Cooperation in Education and Race Relations.
Nathan Carter Newbold married Mabel Wooten in 1900. Wooten was born in La Grange, North Carolina in 1875 and died in 1903. She attended the State Normal and Industrial School in North Carolina (which later became the University of North Carolina at Greensboro) and graduated in 1895.
In 1905 Nathan Carter Newbold married Eugenia Bradsher, who was born in 1875 in Person County. Eugenia Bradsher was a classmate of Mabel Wooten at the State Normal and Industrial School in North Carolina (UNCG) and also graduated in 1895. She died in 1960.
William Newbold was Nathan Carter Newbold's grandfather. He was the Sheriff in Pasquotank in the 1850s and died in 1864.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Collection Overview
Personal and professional papers of Nathan Carter Newbold and his relatives, including his father William A. Newbold and grandfather William Newbold (Sheriff of Pasquotank County, North Carolina), his first wife Mabel Wooten, and his second wife Eugenia Bradsher. The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, photographs, financial and property records dating from the 1840s, and recorded speeches given at Nathan Carter Newbold's retirement dinner. Some photographs have been identified as being of South Carolina during the late 19th century-early 20th century, which include portraits, street scenes (in Charleston), sail boats, as well as a few photographs of people of color, including photographs of "Lascar Sailors."Some photographs are of the U.S. Military Academy at West Point during the 1890s. Many of the legal and financial papers were generated by Nathan Carter Newbold's father and grandfather. The bulk of the correspondence relates to Nathan Carter Newbold's role as an administrator for North Carolina public schools and to his tenure as the Director of the Division of Negro Education during segregation and Jim Crow.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audio materials are CLOSED to researchers. Use copies are available in the collection.
Segregation in education -- North Carolina; Elizabeth City (N.C.) -- History; Pasquotank County (N.C.) -- History; South Carolina -- History; Newbold, Eugenia Lou Bradsher, 1875-1960; Newbold, Mabel Eliza Wooten, 1875-1903; Newbold, N.C. (Nathan Carter), 1871-1957; Newbold, William, 1808-1864; Newbold, William A., 1843-; North Carolina Commission on Interracial Cooperation; North Carolina. Department of Public Instruction. Division of Negro Education; United States Military Academy
- Correspondence, 1895-1952 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Includes personal and professional letters written to and from Eugenia Bradsher Newbold, Nathan Carter Newbold, Mabel Wooten and others. The letters document the courtship between Nathan Carter Newbold and his first wife Mabel Wooten, whom he married in 1900, as well as his later marriage to Eugenia Bradsher. These personal letters reveal the day-to-day experiences of the authors including their affection for one another. Much of the correspondence written to Nathan Carter Newbold is made up of appreciation letters from public school officials who wrote to Newbold upon his retirement. Other correspondence documents Newbold's professional networks (including connections to Trinity College) and depicts his activity within the North Carolina public school system as an administrator.
  - Newbold, Eugenia Bradsher, 1895-1907; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Newbold, Nathan Carter, 1896-1952 and undated; 19 folders (Box 1)
  - Wooten, Mabel, 1898-1902 (Box 1)
    The bulk of the letters are written to Nathan Carter Newbold during their courtship and after their marriage in 1900 in La Grange, North Carolina.
- Legal and Financial, 1840s-1920s and undated; 10 folders
  Receipts, deeds, contracts, wills, and promissory notes. The bulk of the receipts are from business interactions created by William Newbold in Pasquotank County and Elizabeth City in North Carolina. One folder includes receipts made while William Newbold served as the legal guardian for children of the Bright family. Some of the receipts are from taxes collected by William Newbold when he served as Sheriff for Pasquatank County in the 1850s; these receipts list the names of residents and the amounts paid. Additionally, a few of the wills and deeds identify people of color and document the transfer of enslaved people.
  - Guardianship of Bright family receipts, 1850-1865 (Box 1)
  - Receipts, 1840-1860s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Receipts and Deeds, 1840s-1920s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Tax receipts, Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 1873-1885 (Box 1)
  - Tax records of Sheriff William Newbold, Pasquotank County, North Carolina, 1850-1855 (Box 1)
  - Wills, contracts, and promissory notes, 1850s (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1890-1939 and undated
  Many portraits and some landscape scenes taken of family members and unidentified people. Many of the portraits were taken in studios in North Carolina, Virginia, Massachusetts, Texas, and Georgia; and two were taken in the Philippines, perhaps during the Spanish-American War in 1898. Some of the photographs were taken in South Carolina and include street scenes in Charleston, landscapes, and portraits. Some of the photographs are of people of color, including photographs of "Lascar Sailors." Additionally, there are photographs of the United States Military Academy (West Point).
  - Assorted photographs, 1890-1939 and undated; 7 folders (Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
  - South Carolina cyanotypes, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    Various-sized (mostly 3x5) cyanotypes, many with captions. They appear to have been taken in South Carolina. Though they are undated, it is likely they were taken in the late 19th or early 20th century. Many of the prints are stamped "Wm. M. Mackenzie, 16 Glebe St., Charleston, S.C." Photographs include portraits, street scenes, sail boats, as well as a few photographs of people of color, including photographs of "Lascar Sailors."
  - United States Military Academy (West Point), black and white, undated (Box 4)
    Photographs of the grounds of the academy and portraits of William Preston Wooten (class of 1898).
  - United States Military Academy (West Point), cyanotypes, undated (Box 4)
    3x5 photographs with captions of the grounds and buildings of the academy.
- Printed Materials and Ephemera, 1866-1972
  Includes programs, obituaries, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous ephemera. The bulk of the clippings relate to Nathan Carter Newbold's career with the North Carolina public school system.
  - Clippings, 1900-1972 and undated (Box 3)
  - Printed materials, 1889-1928 and undated (Box 3, Oversize-folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1866-1911 and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Writings and Speeches, 1890s-1950 and undated
  Includes writings and speeches by Mabel Wooten and Nathan Carter Newbold and others. Wooten, who graduated from the State Normal and Industrial School in 1895 (which later became the University of North Carolina at Greensboro), writes about pedagogy, manners, and the history of Person County, North Carolina. Nathan Carter Newbold's writings pertain mostly to education and to Christianity. Additionally, there are recordings of speeches made at Newbold's retirement dinner in 1950.
  - Newbold, Nathan Carter, 1950 and undated (Box 3)
  - Testimonial after dinner speeches in honor of Dr. N.C. Newbold, 1950; 6 disks
    - Lacquer phonograph record 1 of 6 (Box 5, Audio-phonodisc RL11544-PD-0001)
    - Lacquer phonograph record 2 of 6 (Box 5, Audio-phonodisc RL11544-PD-0002)
    - Lacquer phonograph record 3 of 6 (Box 5, Audio-phonodisc RL11544-PD-0003)
    - Lacquer phonograph record 4 of 6 (Box 5, Audio-phonodisc RL11544-PD-0004)
    - Lacquer phonograph record 5 of 6 (Box 5, Audio-phonodisc RL11544-PD-0005)
    - Lacquer phonograph record 6 of 6 (Box 5, Audio-phonodisc RL11544-PD-0006)
    - DVD preservation copy (Box 5, Dvd RL11544-DVD-0001)
    - Cassette use copy (Box 3, Audio-cassette RL11544-CS-0001)
    - CD use copy (Box 3, Audio-cd RL11544-CD-0002)
    - CD preservation copy (Box 3, Audio-cd RL11544-CD-0001)
  - Wooten, Mabel, 1890s and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Includes various writings as well as a laboratory manual used during her studies at the State Normal and Industrial School.